I enjoy my coffee and you'll be
hardpressed to remove it from my
screaming hands if this turns out to be
bad news. You may feel the same way.
There's a huge new study including over
100,000 people over an amazing 43 years
that just released a few weeks ago and
goes over the link between coffee and
the risk of brain diseases classically
called dementia. This study has an
incredibly surprising finding from my
perspective, especially considering what
we know about coffee. Anyway, in some
ways, I'm going to tell you some
self-fulfilling great news, and in
others, I'm going to disappoint you.
There's a lot to like about this study.
For example, the researchers
continuously track coffee consumption
every two to four years over the next
four four decades, which is one major
reason that this study is so powerful.
Now, when we look at the data, we see
the risk of dementia on the vertical
axis. Anything below that starting 1.0
is considered reduced risk. Then the
further right that we go, the more
coffee consumed. Clearly, there's a
relationship with reduced risk, which
continues to indicate reduced risk from
zero cups to about three cups of coffee
with little additional benefit going
beyond that. One cup is defined as 8
ounces or about 240 milliliters. The
proposed reason for these benefits stem
from many factors. One major one is the
known way that caffeine molecule binds
to particular types of receptors called
adenosine receptors. Now, it's actually
this receptor that is bound by, you
guessed it, the adenosine molecule,
which accumulates in our body as we go
about our day. It's one of our sleep
pressures. As adenosine rises and binds
to the receptor on our brain cells,
there's a biochemical signal that's
transmitted into the neurons that
promotes drowsiness. Anyway, that's a
bit beside the point, but caffeine binds
those same receptors and changes the
signaling within the neurons, the brain
cells. This change does two things. It
makes brain cells more able to resist
death caused by an accumulation of
proteins like in Alzheimer's disease
called beta amalloid. And secondly, it
can also bind inflammatory cells called
microglea and reduce their production of
pro-inflammatory molecules, which also
protects other brain cells like neurons
from being overly damaged. Now,
apparently there's also evidence that
caffeine suppresses the activity of two
key enzymes involved in producing beta
amalloid called secretasis. Beta
amalloid doesn't just appear in your
brain one day. it's produced and it's
generally found in the insoluble form on
the membrane of your brain cells meaning
it's integrated into the cell membrane.
Then secretases interact with the base
of the amaloid protein and snip it off
creating a soluble version which can
then aggregate and create long-term
issues for cellto cell communication. A
pretty important function if we're
trying to think. Anyway, caffeine
interferes with the activity of these
enzymes that snip the insoluble amaloid
protein. Oh, also caffeine seems to
promote the inhibition of a key enzyme
involved in Alzheimer's disease called
GSK3. Now, if you've been following
physionic for a time, I've mentioned
that sucker a few times. In simple
terms, more GSK3 activity translates to
worse Alzheimer's disease progression.
Now, I won't go into it further than
that, but clearly caffeine and coffee
has many mechanisms by which it can
enact dementia prevention. There's a few
other suggestions based on other studies
done on caffeine, but the bottom line is
this. Coffee reduces risk of dementia,
and there are multiple caffeine related
mechanisms that explain that risk
reduction. I'll likely do a deeper dive
on the mechanisms, but this study isn't
designed to figure out those kinds of
questions. Still, you might have noticed
that I keep referencing caffeine. And
that's not me trying to play slate of
hand between the words caffeine and
coffee. Check this out. We're again
looking at dementia risk with lines
going down indicating reduced dementia
risk. I'm showing you the pool data,
which means that the data based on most
of the participants. The T1 stands for
the lowest coffee consumers and T3 is
the highest. The red shaded area is the
uncertainty in the data. If it crosses
the 1.0 line, that means there's no
statistically identified relationship.
I'm sure you see it now that I've
explained it. The T3 does not indicate a
relationship. So, the more coffee
consumed, no reduced risk of dementia.
This flies in the face of the data that
we just went over a bit ago, right? We
saw that coffee reduced the risk of
dementia, and now we don't. Well, that's
where this focus on caffeine comes in
because we're looking at decaffeinated
coffee here. Exactly why this is the
case is unclear. I mean, we even see a
moderate amount of decaffeinated coffee
does reduce the risk of dementia. So,
why would more reverse that benefit? But
the bad news doesn't end there. Before I
touch on that, you might be interested
to know if you're a tea drinker, how tea
does against dementia or how coffee
affects different forms of dementia or
different preparations of coffee,
sweetened or artificially sweetened, and
their impact or other such details. If
you're inclined, I cover all of that in
my full analysis of the one that you're
currently watching. It's part of my
Physionic Insider membership. You also
get a delivered article, shortened
summary of the main takeaways, and as
usual, all these perks right over here.
If you're a health science nerd like me,
the Physic Insiders is where to be.
Check it out by using the link in the
description. I hope to talk with you
there. Now, back to the bad news. If we
ask people questions related to their
subjective sense of mental performance,
we get some more troublesome results
shown here. The purple is decaffeinated
in this dis in this situation. The
higher the bars go, the worse, meaning
the greater subjective sense of
cognitive decline. So either no
relationship for caffeinated coffee or a
reduced sense of cognitive impairment,
but decaffeinated indicates a stronger
sense of cognitive impairment. There
were some of the same trends seen in
objective measures of cognitive function
as well, though the results weren't
universal. So, what to make of these
data? Well, the researchers argue that
these worrying results for decaffeinated
coffee may be an artifact of
confounding, meaning people consuming
decaffeinated coffee may have caffeine
intolerances and underlying health
concerns that predispose them to
cognitive decline. Truthfully, this is
just guesswork because the researchers
did perform robust adjustments and still
found this association. I also think
that the assumption that tens of
thousands of people are all suffering
from a similar health issue that are not
adjusted for and that forces them to
consume decaffeinated coffee is a bit of
a stretch in my mind. But maybe my
caffeine saturated brain is deceiving
me. I'd be open to this interpretation,
but I would want to actually see data
indicating that it's to be true. I
currently remain skeptical. Still, we
don't need to rely on this study. We can
expand our view to other similar studies
and see if these results remain true.
For example, another huge though less
robust analysis indicates similar
striking differences between caffeinated
and decaffeinated coffee. This analysis
does not indicate harm of decaffeinated
coffee, but it does confirm unique
benefits of caffeinated coffee that are
not seen in any measure of decaffeinated
coffee. Unfortunately, there aren't any
longerterm randomized control trials
between caffeinated and decaffeinated
coffee on cognitive outcomes. There's a
few smaller short-term studies, and they
seem to confirm that there may actually
be differences between caffeinated and
decaffeinated with caffeinated offering
more potent benefits. That said, they
also don't generally argue decaffeinated
leads to worse outcomes. So, that was a
lot. I realize I'll put it to you this
way. The data for dementia indicates
that there's robust protective effect of
caffeinated coffee on average about an
18% reduced risk with more questions for
decaffeinated coffee. I don't think that
we should necessarily demonize deca
decaffeinated coffee. Now, I'd say that
the data leans more toward a null
effect. This means that there may be
some unique benefit of caffeinated
coffee, assuming that you can tolerate
it. I imagine you aren't just interested
in your brain health, though, if I'm
reading your face correctly. Obviously,
I'm pretending because I'm looking at a
camera, but pretend with me. If you're
interested in other benefits of coffee,
then check out this video right here. I
go over heart health and more, but also
how timing your coffee makes a big
difference on your health. You won't
want to miss it. I can feel it. Thanks
for hanging out and I'll catch you in
the next one. See you.